Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin

Zürich, Switzerland ibo.mohsin@gmail.com

Last Updated: August, 2022

https://ibomohsin.github.io/ linkedin.com/in/ibrahimalabdulmohsin/

I am a research scientist at Google Brain, developing tools for understanding deep learning and improving its societal impact, particularly relating to fairness. Previously, I founded and led the Advanced Analytics team at Saudi Aramco, managed the company's Enterprise Analytics program, and was a technical lead at its digital transformation program.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Computer Science, KAUST, GPA: 4.0 / 4.0

Thesis title: "Learning via Query Synthesis." Committee: X. Zhang, X. Gao, D. Keyes (KAUST), and W. Wang (UCLA). 2012 — 2017

Master of Science, Electrical Engineering, Stanford University, GPA: 4.15 / 4.0

Emphasis on networked systems, artificial intelligence, and operations management. 2009 — 2011

Bachelor of Science, Computer Engineering, University of Nebraska, Lincoln, GPA: 3.98 / 4.0

Highest Distinction; Superior Scholarship Award; Minor in Economics. 2000 — 2005

SKILLS

Research & Development Authored 1 book, +25 research papers, 1 granted patent and 3 pending patents.

Communication English (fluent), Arabic (native), German (elementary, A1).

Technical Data science, artificial intelligence, modeling & optimization, digital transformation, networked systems

(certified by Cisco, Juniper and Alcatel-Lucent).

Leadership +2 years managing corporate-wide enterprise analytics program, leading the data science team, and serv-

ing as a technical lead at the digital transformation program at Saudi Aramco.

SELECTED ACTIVITIES

Google, Brain Team

Program committee member at NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, and IJCAI.

Reviewer for TMLR, IEEE PAMI, IEEE TNNLS, and IEEE Communications Letters.

Member of the S20 Task Force (Digital Revolution).

Chair of AI track of the 2019 Arab-American Frontiers Symposium.

2017 — Present
2019 — Present
2020
2020

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH & DEVELOPMENT SCIENTIST

NOV 2019 — Present

Zürich, Switzerland

- Led / co-led several projects to improve understanding of deep learning and improve ML fairness; e.g. pretraining with random labels, debiasing neural networks, debiasing multiclass datasets, data scaling laws, reinitialization and calibration.
- Key member of a moonshot team for machine learning fairness in healthcare.
- Member of the Google Scholarship review team and mentor of AI residents.

LEAD, ADVANCED ANALYTICS

 $\mathsf{NOV}\,2017-\mathsf{OCT}\,2019$

Saudi Aramco, Corporate Applications Dept

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- Founded and led the Advanced Analytics team that was responsible for developing AI solutions, managing analytics infrastructures, conducting research collaboration with academia, evaluating technologies, and developing roadmaps.
- Technical lead at the Digital Transformation Program, with a mission to accelerate the adoption of artificial intelligence at the company.
- Led the design & implementation of several ML applications in sectors such as downstream, supply chain, sales & marketing, IT,
 cybersecurity and HR.

NETWORK PERFORMANCE ENGINEER

JUN 2011 — AUG 2012

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

Saudi Aramco, Comm. Eng. Department

Saudi Aramco, Comm. Eng. Department

- Won the Operation Services Business Line recognition award (2012) for "distinguished achievements."
- Performance management and capacity planning for enterprise communications services such as the Data Center, the Internet, Extranet, and Wireless LAN infrastructures.
- Developed an analytics tool for automated performance analysis and SLA compliance assessment.

DATA NETWORK ENGINEER

JUL 2005 — AUG 2009

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- Won the Information Technology Admin Area recognition award (2007) for "developing innovative solutions" and the Communications Eng Dept recognition award (2009) for "significant contributions to department's success."
- Key member of an 18-month IT network security project for securing critical facilities.
- Project manager for a 1-year CCTV surveillance camera systems project (involving civil and communications work).
- Design, installation, configuration, reviews, upgrades, and troubleshooting of data networks.